Finding Aid for Carey Pratt McCord Papers 1913-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carey Pratt McCord Papers 1913-1978
McCord, Carey Pratt, 1886-
Industrial hygienist, consultant and lecturer in environmental and industrial health in the School of Public Health of the University of Michigan. Logs of daily activities, 1936-1961, correspondence relating to consulting projects, speech and lecture material, and research files on lead poisoning and the effects of air conditioning on workers; history of occupational health at the University of Michigan, 1873-1970, history of the American Academy of Occupational Medicine, 1946-1956; history of the Bernardino Ramazzini Society, 1942-1978; study of automobile body industry in Detroit, 1936; and related photographs.
85309 Aa 2
5.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Dr. McCord (donor no. 6038 ) donated his papers to the library in 1977. Additional materials were accessioned in 2003 through the UM School of Public Health.
The collection is open for research.
Carey Pratt McCord was born on September 25, 1886 in Bibb County, Alabama, the son of a Baptist minister. In 1907 he received a bachelor's degree from Howard College in Birmingham. He then came to Ann Arbor and studied medicine, earning a medical degree from the University of Michigan in 1912.
After graduating from Michigan, McCord began his professional career as a research physiologist in the laboratories of the Parke-Davis and Company in Detroit. His research at this time centered upon the functioning of glands during the body's fetal period.
After four years with Parke-Davis, McCord left the firm to enter a field of medicine which was just developing: occupational health. McCord's pathbreaking work led him to be labeled one of the "big five" pioneers in industrial and occupational health. He served as a consultant for numerous firms, including the Chrysler Corporation where he worked for 16 years. He published over 20 books and 3,000 articles. Much of this work was done as the director of the Industrial Health Conservancy Laboratories, an organization which specialized in research about toxicology. McCord headed the organization from 1919 until 1951.
In addition to his responsibilities as a researcher and an industrial consultant, McCord served in governmental and educational posts. He was director of Industrial Hygiene for Detroit's Department of Health from 1937 until 1940. He also served two years as director of the Michigan State Board of Health's Department of Industrial Health.
McCord was an associate professor of preventative medicine at the University of Cincinnati between 1920 and 1935. In 1937 he joined the faculty of the medical school at Wayne University in Detroit. In 1940 he retired from Wayne to join the faculty of the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan. He continued to serve at Michigan as a lecturer and a consultant for thirty five years.
McCord retired from active work in 1976, returning to his home in Cincinnati, Ohio. He died October 14, 1979 in Appleton, Wisconsin.
The papers of Carey Pratt McCord represent only a fragment of what once must have been a larger body of papers and consequently document only a small portion of his varied and active career. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Personal; Correspondence; Speeches and lectures; Writings and related; Research files; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Air conditioning.; American Academy of Occupational Medicine.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Detroit.; Work environment--Michigan.; Lead poisoning.; McCord, Carey Pratt, 1886-; Occupational diseases.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Bakeries--Michigan--Detroit.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Offices.; Restaurants--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  - Autobiography A Blind Hog's Acorns, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Acorns and Truffles, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (Original draft of A Blind Hog's Acorns)
  - Qualifications/Resume 1933-1968 (Box 1)
  - Certificates (Box 1)
  - Retirement letters and publications 1951 (Box 1)
  - Retirement publicity 1976 (Box 1)
  - Log of activities
    - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1941 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - By date
    - 1913-1917 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1921 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1942-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1977 (Box 1)
  - By subject
    - American Medical Association (Box 2)
    - Bohn Aluminum (Box 2)
    - DeFender Company
      (See also Correspondence: Ear defenders)
      - General (Box 2)
      - Vern O. Knudsen (Box 2)
      - Technical data (Box 2)
    - Ear defenders (Mine Safety Appliances Co. and V.O. Knudsen), 3 folders (Box 2)
      (See also Correspondence: DeFender Company)
    - E.R. Hayhurst (Box 2)
    - Industrial Medicine-A.D. McCloud (Box 2)
    - Industrial Medicine Council, American Medical Association (Box 2)
    - Kegan and Kegan, patent attorneys (Box 2)
    - Kellogg's of Battle Creek (Box 2)
    - Lelard Electric Company (Box 2)
    - Lowe Brothers of Dayton, Ohio (Box 2)
    - Ozone Sales and Service Company (Box 2)
    - Pittsburgh Plate Glass (Box 2)
    - Pullman Company (Box 2)
    - Martin Senour Company (Box 2)
    - Sherwin Williams Company (Box 2)
    - University Library-University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - Wolverine Brass Works (Box 2)
- Speeches and lectures
  There are a number of drafts of Speeches and lectures on industrial health topics given in front of various audiences, including colleagues and medical students at the University of Michigan.
  - 1920s (Box 2)
  - 1942 (California) (Box 2)
  - 1948 (Birmingham) (Box 2)
  - 1965 from Award Remarks (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Speech material (Box 2)
- Writings and related
  Writings and related contain a small selection of the 3,000 articles authored during his career, and reports written in the 1930s at the Industrial Health Conservancy Laboratories concerning occupational diseases and working conditions.
  - Bibliographies of McCord's works, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - The Scourge of Survey
    - Correspondence 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Man in Conflict with His Environments" (Box 3)
  - Articles by McCord, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Articles submitted for publishing
    - "Race Poisons, The Pregnant Woman in Industry" (Box 3)
    - "The Toxicology of the Unborn" (Box 3)
  - Editorials by McCord (Box 3)
  - Book reviews (Box 3)
  - Reports for Consumer Research Inc. 1932 (Box 3)
  - A Study of the Automobile Body Industry in Detroit circa 1936 (Box 3)
  - Reports for Industrial Health Conservancy Laboratories
    - Toxicity of carbon tetrachloride and related substances undated (Box 3)
    - The lead problem at the Briggs Manufacturing Company 1935 (Box 3)
    - Literature, notes & excerpts referable to occupational disease legislation circa 1935 (Box 3)
    - Compilation of current occupational disease laws in the United States circa 1935 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous information on the costs of occupational disease insurance 1936 (Box 3)
    - A limited investigation of carbon monoxide hazard in the motor bus division of the department of street railways in Detroit, Michigan 1935 (Box 3)
    - Basophilic aggregation test for lead absorption and lead poisoning-Ten years after its first use 1935 (Box 3)
    - Benzol (Benzene) poisoning: A new investigation of the toxicity of Benzene and Benzene impurities 1931 (Box 3)
  - Reports on the health of the workers of the Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company 1933-1934, 3 folders (Box 3)
    (includes photographs)
  - Reports on the health of the workers of the Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company 1933-1934, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Research files
  The Research files are the only surviving fragments of the over 4,000 such projects McCord conducted. In some cases, the material in the Correspondence and Writings series relates to research projects.
  - Air conditioning, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Cancer research (Box 4)
  - Carbon monoxide (Box 4)
  - Carbon tetrachloride (Box 4)
  - Lead, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Porphyrins (Box 4)
  - Refrigerants (Box 4)
  - American Train Dispatchers, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Turpentine (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  The collection also includes within the Miscellaneous series the history of several organizations with which McCord was associated. Of particular note is the history of the Bernardino Ramazzini Society, an honor fraternity of industrial physicians founded in part by McCord in 1942. The Society took its name from the patron saint and father of the industrial health field, a 17th century Italian physician who studied the diseases associated with workers. There are also a number of interview transcripts conducted in the early 1960s with leaders in the field of industrial health.
  - Interviews, 5 folders (Box 5)
    (Includes transcripts and related correspondence)
  - Bernadino Ramazzini Society
    - Correspondence 1942 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1952-1954 (Box 5)
    - History
      - 1959 (Box 5)
      - 1967-1974 (Box 5)
    - General 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Organization of Industrial Hygienist Association 1938 (Box 5)
  - History of Occupational Health at University of Michigan 1873-1970 (Box 5)
  - History of the American Academy of Occupational Medicine 1946-1956 (Box 5)
  - United States Army (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook material (Box 5)
  - Interesting cases for publication (Box 5)
  - Court cases in which McCord testified
    - Karl Baumman 1928-1933 (Box 5)
      (arsenic poisoning)
    - Dura Company 1928-1933 (Box 5)
      (lead poisoning and gender discrimination in industry)
    - Lavelette and Mary Worsham 1929-1931 (Box 5)
      (sulphur dioxide exposure from refrigeration)
- Photographs
  Photographs relate to some of McCord's work and document his professional activity through conferences and meetings of the Bernandino Ramazzini Society.
  - Lighting--includes views of Proctor and Gamble Crisco plant (Box 6)
  - Mechanical Safeguarding (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Switching Stations (Trains) (Box 6)
  - Industrial Restrooms--includes new worker facilities in light and heavy industry factories (Box 6)
  - Ventilation--includes views of Detroit bakeries and restaurant illustrating use of fans in operation (Box 6)
  - Shot towers (Box 6)
  - Personal (Box 6)
    (includes photographs of McCord)
  - Colleagues (Box 6)
  - Conferences and meetings, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - General Motors/Chrysler (Box 6)
  - School of Public Health, University of Michigan 1959 (Box 6)
  - Bernardino Ramazzini Society, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Bernardino Ramazzini (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)